I want to share some personal friends and stories with you
أود أن أشارككم بعضاً من الأصدقاء و القصص الشخصية
that I've actually never talked about in public before
والتي لم أتكلم عنها بشكل عام من قبل أبداً
to help illustrate the idea
للمساعدة على توضيح الفكرة
and the need and the hope
والحاجة والأمل
for us to reinvent our health care system around the world.
لإعادة تأسيس نظام للرعاية الصحية في جميع أنحاء العالم.
Twenty-four years ago, I had -- a sophomore in college,
قبل أربعة وعشرين عاماً، كنت طالب في السنة الثانية في الكلية،
I had a series of fainting spells. No alcohol was involved.
كنت قد أصبت بسلسلة من نوبات الإغماء. دون دخل للكحول في الموضوع.
And I ended up in student health,
وانتهى بي الأمر في المركز الصحي للطلاب،
and they ran some labwork and came back right away,
وأجروا بعض التحاليل و ظهرت نتائج التحليل على الفور،
and said, "Kidney problems."
وقالوا لي "مشاكل في الكلى."
And before I knew it, I was involved and thrown into
وقبل أن أعلم، أشركوني و ألقوني في
this six months of tests and trials and tribulations
ستة أشهر من الاختبارات والتجارب والمحن
with six doctors across two hospitals
مع ستة أطباء من مستشفيين
in this clash of medical titans
في صراع بين جبابرة في الطب
to figure out which one of them was right
لمعرفة أي واحد منهم كان على حق
about what was wrong with me.
حول مشكلتي.
And I'm sitting in a waiting room some time later for an ultrasound,
ثم جلست في غرفة الانتظار بعدها بفترة لعمل أشعة موجات فوق الصوتية،
and all six of these doctors actually show up in the room at once,
وحضر ستة الأطباء جميعهم في الغرفة في وقت واحد،
and I'm like, "Uh oh, this is bad news."
وكانت ردة فعلي " أوه، إنها أخبار سيئة."
And their diagnosis was this:
وكان تشخيصهم كالآتي:
They said, "You have two rare kidney diseases
قالوا، "لديك اثنين من أمراض الكلى النادرة
that are going to actually destroy your kidneys eventually,
والتي ستدمر الكليتين في نهاية المطاف،
you have cancer-like cells in your immune system
لديك خلايا تشبه خلايا السرطان في جهازك المناعي
that we need to start treatment right away,
ونحتاج إلى بدء العلاج فوراً،
and you'll never be eligible for a kidney transplant,
ولن تكون مؤهلاً لعملية زرع الكلى،
and you're not likely to live more than two or three years."
ومن المحتمل أنك لن تعيش أكثر من عامين أو ثلاثة أعوام ."
Now, with the gravity of this doomsday diagnosis,
و مع خطورة هذا التشخيص ،
it just sucked me in immediately,
فقد احبطني فورا،
as if I began preparing myself as a patient
كما لو كنت بدأت بتجهيز نفسي كمريض
to die according to the schedule that they had just given to me,
لأن أموت طبقاً للجدول الزمني الذي اعطونيه للتو،
until I met a patient named Verna in a waiting room,
حتى التقيت بمريض اسمها فيرنا في غرفة الانتظار،
who became a dear friend, and she grabbed me one day
التي أصبحت صديقة عزيزة علي، فأمسكت بي يوماً ما
and took me off to the medical library
وجرتني إلى المكتبة الطبية
and did a bunch of research on these diagnoses and these diseases,
وقامت بموجموعة من البحوث بشأن هذه التشخيصات وهذه الأمراض،
and said, "Eric, these people who get this
وقالت: "إريك، هؤلاء الناس الذين يفهمون هذا
are normally in their '70s and '80s.
عادة في السبعينيات و الثمنانيات من أعمارهم.
They don't know anything about you. Wake up.
لا يعرفون أي شيء عنك. استيقظ.
Take control of your health and get on with your life."
تحكم بصحتك و تمتع بحياتك."
And I did.
ولقد فعلت ذلك.
Now, these people making these proclamations to me
هؤلاء الناس الذين يقومون بالتشخيصات هذه
were not bad people.
ليسوا سيئين.
In fact, these professionals were miracle workers,
في الواقع، كان هؤلاء المختصين صانعي المعجزات،
but they're working in a flawed, expensive system that's set up the wrong way.
لكنهم يعملون في نظام معيب مكلف تم إعداده بطريقة خاطئة.
It's dependent on hospitals and clinics for our every care need.
فهو يعتمد على المستشفيات والعيادات لكل ما نحتاجه من عناية.
It's dependent on specialists who just look at parts of us.
ويعتمد على الأخصائيين الذين ينظرون إلى جزء منا وحسب.
It's dependent on guesswork of diagnoses and drug cocktails,
ويعتمد على التخمين من التشخيصات وخليط من العقاقير،
and so something either works or you die.
و إما أن يعمل شيئاً ما او أن تموت.
And it's dependent on passive patients
وهو يعتمد على مرضىً مستسلمين
who just take it and don't ask any questions.
يقبلون به ولا يسألون أي أسئلة.
Now the problem with this model
والآن مشكلة هذا النموذج
is that it's unsustainable globally.
هو أنه غير مستدام على الصعيد العالمي.
It's unaffordable globally.
ولا يمكن تحمل نفقاته على الصعيد العالمي.
We need to invent what I call a personal health system.
نحن بحاجة إلى ابتكار ما اسميه بنظام صحة شخصي.
So what does this personal health system look like,
إذاً كيف يبدو شكل النظام الصحي الشخصي هذا،
and what new technologies and roles is it going to entail?
وما هي التكنولوجيات والأدوار الجديدة الذي سيترتب عليه؟
Now, I'm going to start by actually sharing with you
والآن، سأبدأ بمشاركتكم
a new friend of mine, Libby,
صديق جديد لي، ليبي
somebody I've become quite attached to over the last six months.
وهي شخص أصبحت متعلق بها تماماً خلال الأشهر الستة الماضية.
This is Libby, or actually, this is an ultrasound image of Libby.
هذه هي ليبي، أو في الواقع، هذه صورة موجات فوق الصوتية لليبي.
This is the kidney transplant I was never supposed to have.
وهذه هي زرع الكلى الذي كان من المفترض أن لا أجريه أبداً.
Now, this is an image that we shot a couple of weeks ago for today,
والآن، هذه صورة التقطناها قبل أسبوعين من اليوم،
and you'll notice, on the edge of this image,
وستلاحظون، على حافة هذه الصورة،
there's some dark spots there, which was really concerning to me.
هناك بعض البقع الداكنة، والتي أقلقتني حقاً.
So we're going to actually do a live exam
لذا سنقوم بامتحان مباشرة
to sort of see how Libby's doing.
لنرى كيف تفعل ليبي.
This is not a wardrobe malfunction. I have to take my belt off here.
هذا ليس عطلاً بخزانة ملابسي. يتحتم علي أن أخلع حزامي.
Don't you in the front row worry or anything.
لا تقلقوا أيها الجالسين في الصف الأمامي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'm going to use a device from a company called Mobisante.
سأستخدم جهاز من شركة تسمى موبيسانتي.
This is a portable ultrasound.
وهذا جهاز موجات فوق الصوتية محمول.
It can plug into a smartphone. It can plug into a tablet.
يمكنكم توصيله بالهاتف ذكي. يمكنكم توصيل إلى كمبيوتر لوحي.
Mobisante is up in Redmond, Washington,
موبيسانتي يوجد في في ريدموند، واشنطن،
and they kindly trained me to actually do this on myself.
وقد دربوني بكل لطف على القيام بذلك بنفسي.
They're not approved to do this. Patients are not approved to do this.
وهم غير مصرحون للقيام بهذا. المرضى ليسوا مصرحون للقيام بذلك.
This is a concept demo, so I want to make that clear.
هذه تجرية مفاهيمية، وأرغب أن أوضح الأمر.
All right, I gotta gel up.
حسناً، يجب أن أضيف بعض الجل.
Now the people in the front row are very nervous. (Laughter)
والأشخاص الجالسون في الصف الأمامي قلقون جداً. (ضحك)
And I want to actually introduce you to Dr. Batiuk,
وأريد أن أعرفكم بالدكتور باتوك،
who's another friend of mine.
وهو صديق آخر لي.
He's up in Legacy Good Samaritan Hospital in Portland, Oregon.
يوجد في مستشفى ليقاسي جود ساماريتان في بورتلاند، أوريغون.
So let me just make sure. Hey, Dr. Batiuk. Can you hear me okay?
اسمحوا لي أن أتأكد فقط. أهلاً، دكتور باتوك. هل تسمعني؟
And actually, can you see Libby?
هل يمكنك أن ترى ليبي؟
Thomas Batuik: Hi there, Eric.
توماس باتوك: مرحبا اريك.
You look busy. How are you?
تبدو مشغولاً. كيف حالك؟
Eric Dishman: I'm good. I'm just taking my clothes off
إيريك ديشمان: أنا جيد. أنا أقوم بخلع ملابسي فقط.
in front of a few hundred people. It's wonderful.
أمام مئات من الأشخاص. أنه رائع.
So I just wanted to see, is this the image you need to get?
أردت فقط أن انظر، هل هذه الصورة التي تحتاجها؟
And I know you want to look and see if those spots are still there.
وأنا أعلم أنك تريد أن ترى ما إذا كانت تلك البقع لا تزال هنا.
TB: Okay. Well let's scan around a little bit here,
ت.ب:حسنا دعونا نمسح المنطقة هنا قليلاً
give me a lay of the land.
بين لي المنطقة جيداً
ED: All right.TB: Okay. Turn it a little bit inside,
أ.د: حسناً.ت.ب: أدره قليلاً إلى الداخل،
a little bit toward the middle for me.
نحو الوسط قليلاً.
Okay, that's good. How about up a little bit?
حسنا، هذا جيد. ما رأيك برفعه قليلاً للأعلى؟
Okay, freeze that image. That's a good one for me.
حسنا، قف على تلك الصورة. هذا هي جيدة لي.
ED: All right. Now last week, when I did this,
أ.د: حسناً. في الأسبوع الماضي، عندما فعلت هذا، الأسبوع السابق،
you had me measure that spot to the right.
جعلتني أقيس تلك البقعة في اليمين.
Should I do that again?
هل ينبغي علي أن أفعل ذلك مرة أخرى؟
TB: Yeah, let's do that.
ت.ب: نعم، دعنا نفعل ذلك.
ED: All right. This is kind of hard to do
أ.د: حسناً. يصعب القيام بذلك نوعاً ما.
with one hand on your belly and one hand on measuring,
بيد واحدة على بطنك ويداً أخرى على القياس،
but I've got it, I think,
ولكني توصلت إليه، على ما أعتقد،
and I'll save that image and send it to you.
سأحفظ تلك الصورة وأرسلها إليك.
So tell me a little bit about what this dark spot means.
أخبرني قليلاً حول ما تعنيه هذه البقعة الغامقة.
It's not something I was very happy about.
هي ليست شيئا كنت سعيداً جداً حوله.
TB: Many people after a kidney transplant
ت.ب: كثير من الناس بعد عملية زرع الكلي
will develop a little fluid collection around the kidney.
سيصابون بتجمع سوائل قليل حول الكلي.
Most of the time it doesn't create any kind of mischief,
و في معظم الوقت لا تشكل أي أذى
but it does warrant looking at,
لكنها تستدعي الكشوفات الاحترازية،
so I'm happy we've got an opportunity to look at it today,
لذلك أنا سعيد أننا حصلنا على فرصة للنظر إليه اليوم،
make sure that it's not growing, it's not creating any problems.
للتأكد من أنه لا ينمو، وإنه لا يخلق أية مشاكل.
Based on the other images we have,
استناداً إلى صور الأخرى لدينا،
I'm really happy how it looks today.
أنا سعيد حقاً حول شكلها اليوم.
ED: All right. Well, I guess we'll double check it when I come in.
أ.د: حسناً. أعتقد أننا سنفحصه مره أخرى عندما أأتي.
I've got my six month biopsy in a couple of weeks,
وأنا على موعد مع إجراء خزعة الستة أشهر بعد أسبوعين
and I'm going to let you do that in the clinic,
وسأجعلكم تقومون بذلك في العيادة،
because I don't think I can do that one on myself.
لأنني لا أعتقد أنه يمكنني أن أفعل ذلك لوحدي.
TB: Good choice.ED: All right, thanks, Dr. Batiuk.
ت.ب: اختيار جيد.أ.د: شكراً دكتور باتوك
All right. So what you're sort of seeing here
حسنًا. ما ترونه هنا نوعاً ما
is an example of disruptive technologies,
هو مثال لتكنولوجيات تجديدية،
of mobile, social and analytic technologies.
تكنولوجيات متنقلة واجتماعية وتحليلية.
These are the foundations of what's going to make personal health possible.
هذه هي الأسس التي ستجعل الصحة الشخصية ممكنة.
Now there's really three pillars
هناك ثلاثة أركان
of this personal health I want to talk to you about now,
لهذه الصحة الشخصية التي أريد أن أحدثكم عنها
and it's care anywhere, care networking and care customization.
وهي رعاية في أي مكان، رعاية شبكية، تخصيص الرعاية.
And you just saw a little bit of the first two
وقد شاهدتم للتو قليلاً من الأول والثاني
with my interaction with Dr. Batiuk.
مع تفاعلي مع الدكتور باتاك.
So let's start with care anywhere.
لذا دعونا نبدأ بالرعية في أي مكان.
Humans invented the idea of hospitals and clinics
اخترع البشر فكرة المستشفيات والعيادات
in the 1780s. It is time to update our thinking.
في سبعينات القرن الثامن عشر. وقد آن الأوان لتحديث تفكيرنا.
We have got to untether clinicians and patients
وعلينا الأن أن نقطع الحبل بين أخصائيي العيادات والمرضى
from the notion of traveling to a special
إستناداً على فكرة السفر الى مكان مخصوص
bricks-and-mortar place for all of our care,
مكان ومبنى حقيقي يحتوي على كل وسائل الرعاية لنا
because these places are often the wrong tool,
لأن هذه الأماكن غالباً ما تكون الأداة الخاطئة،
and the most expensive tool, for the job.
والأداة الأكثر كلفة، للحصول على المطلوب.
And these are sometimes unsafe places to send our sickest patients,
وفي بعض الأحيان هذه الأماكن غير آمنة لإرسال الأكثر مرضاً لها،
especially in an era of superbugs
لا سيما في عصر الفيروسات الفائقة
and hospital-acquired infections.
وأنواع العدوى المكتسبة من المستشفيات.
And many countries are going to go brickless from the start
وهنالك العديد من البلدان التي ستبدأ بتقديم االرعاية اللامكانية منذ البداية
because they're never going to be able to afford
نظراً لأنها لن تكون قادرة على تحمل
the mega-medicalplexes that a lot of the rest of the world has built.
المنشآت الطبية الضخمة التي قامت كثير من دول العالم ببنائها.
Now I personally learned that hospitals
وقد علمت شخصيا أن هذه المستشفيات
can be a very dangerous place at a young age.
يمكن أن تكون مكاناً خطيرا جداً لو كان المريض في سن مبكرة.
This was me in third grade.
هذا هو أنا في الصف الثالث.
I broke my elbow very seriously, had to have surgery,
وقد كسرت كوعي، بشكل خطير، وتوجب علي أن أخضع لعملية جراحية،
worried that they were going to actually lose the arm.
وكنت قلقا بأنهم كانوا على وشك بتر الذراع.
Recovering from the surgery in the hospital, I get bedsores.
وبينما كنت أتعافى من الجراحة في المستشفى، بدأت أتعرض لقرحة الفراش.
Those bedsores become infected,
فبدأت تقرحات الفراش بالالتهاب،
and they give me an antibiotic which I end up being allergic to,
فأعطوني مضادا حيويا كان جسمي يتحسس منه،
and now my whole body breaks out,
فانهار جسمي على إثره بالكامل،
and now all of those become infected.
ثم تعرض كل هؤلاء للالتهاب.
The longer I stayed in the hospital, the sicker I became,
وكلما طالت فترة مكوثي في المستشفى، ازداد بي المرض،
and the more expensive it became,
وازدادت تكاليف العلاج بالنسبة لي،
and this happens to millions of people around the world every year.
وهذا يحدث لملايين الناس في جميع أنحاء العالم كل سنة.
The future of personal health that I'm talking about
إن مستقبل الصحة الشخصية التي أتحدث عنه
says care must occur at home as the default model,
يقول: يجب أن تكون الرعاية في المنزل كنموذج ابتدائي،
not in a hospital or clinic.
لا في المستشفى أو العيادة.
You have to earn your way into those places
إذ لابد أن تبرهن على حاجتك لتلك الأماكن
by being sick enough to use that tool for the job.
بأن تكون مريضاً بما يكفي لاستخدام هذه الأدوات.
Now the smartphones that we're already carrying
والآن، الهواتف الذكية التي نحملها بشكل يومي
can clearly have diagnostic devices like ultrasounds plugged into them,
يمكن لها أن تحمل أجهزة تشخيصية مثل الموجات فوق الصوتية الموصولة بها،
and a whole array of others, today,
ومجموعة كاملة من آجهزة أخرى، اليوم،
and as sensing is built into these,
وبعد أن تدمج المجسات فيها،
we'll be able to do vital signs monitor
فسنكون قادرين على القيام بمراقبة العلامات الحيوية
and behavioral monitoring like we've never had before.
ورصد السلوك الحيوي بطرق لم نصل إليها من قبل.
Many of us will have implantables that will actually look
والعديد منا سوف تكون داخلهم مستزرعات سوف تقوم بالبحث
real-time at what's going on with our blood chemistry
في الوقت الحقيقي المباشر بما يحدث في تفاعلات دمنا
and in our proteins right now.
وفي البروتينات لدينا في الوقت الراهن.
Now the software is also getting smarter, right?
لا سيما وأن البرامج تزداد ذكاءً، أليس كذلك؟
Think about a coach, an agent online,
فكروا في موجه، وكيلاً على الإنترنت،
that's going to help me do safe self-care.
سيساعدني أن أقوم ببعض الرعاية الشخصية الآمنة.
That same interaction that we just did with the ultrasound
وهذا التفاعل نفسه الذي قمنا به بالموجات فوق الصوتية
will likely have real-time image processing,
من المحتمل أن يكون فيه معالج مباشر للصور،
and the device will say, "Up, down, left, right,
وسيقول الجهاز لنا، "أعلى، أسفل، يسار، يمين،
ah, Eric, that's the perfect spot to send that image
آه، إريك، هذا هو المكان المثالي لإرسال تلك الصورة
off to your doctor."
أرسل إلى الطبيب ".
Now, if we've got all these networked devices
الآن، إذا كان لدينا كل هذه الأجهزة المتصلة بالشبكة
that are helping us to do care anywhere,
التي ستساعدها للقيام بالرعاية في أي مكان،
it stands to reason that we also need a team
فمن الوجيه أننا أيضا سنحتاج إلى فريق
to be able to interact with all of that stuff,
ليتمكن من التفاعل مع كل تلك الأشياء،
and that leads to the second pillar I want to talk about,
وهو ما سيقودنا إلى الركيزة الثانية التي أريد أن أتحدث عنها،
care networking.
شبكات الرعاية.
We have got to go beyond this paradigm
يجب علينا أن نتخطى هذا النموذج التصوري
of isolated specialists doing parts care
المبني على أخصائيين منعزلين يقومون بالرعاية على حده
to multidisciplinary teams doing person care.
نحو فرق متعددة الاختصاصات تقوم برعاية شخصية شاملة
Uncoordinated care today is expensive at best,
إن لرعاية غير المنسقة اليوم هي مكلفة في أحسن الأحوال،
and it is deadly at worst.
وهي قاتلة في أسوأ الأحوال.
Eighty percent of medical errors are actually caused
إن نسبة ثمانين في المائة من الأخطاء الطبية هي في الواقع
by communication and coordination problems
نتيجة مشاكل في الاتصال والتنسيق
amongst medical team members.
بين أعضاء الفريق الطبي.
I had my own heart scare years ago in graduate school,
وقد نزل علي خوف عمري منذ سنوات عندما كنت في كلية الدراسات العليا،
when we're under treatment for the kidney,
عندما كنت خاضعا لعلاج الكلى،
and suddenly, they're like, "Oh, we think you have a heart problem."
فجأة، سمعتهم يقولون، "أوه، نحن نعتقد أن لديك مشكلة في القلب."
And I have these palpitations that are showing up.
ثم أرى ذلك الخفقان يظهر بوضوح.
They put me through five weeks of tests --
فأخضعوني لفحوصات استغرقت خمسة أسابيع -
very expensive, very scary -- before the nurse finally notices
هي مكلفة جداً، ومخيفة جداً-- قبل أن تلاحظ الممرضة أخيرا
the piece of the paper, my meds list
قصاصة الورق التي تحوي قائمة أدويتي
that I've been carrying to every single appointment,
التي كنت أحملها لكل موعد،
and says, "Oh my gosh."
فقالت لي، "يا إلهي."
Three different specialists had prescribed
لقد قام ثلاثة أخصائيون مختلفين بوصف
three different versions of the same drug to me.
ثلاثة ماركات مختلفة من نفس الدواء.
I did not have a heart problem. I had an overdose problem.
إذاً فأنا لم أكن أعاني من مشكلة في القلب. بل كنت أعاني من مشكلة جرعة زائدة.
I had a care coordination problem.
كنت أعاني مشكلة تنسيق في الرعاية.
And this happens to millions of people every year.
وهذا يحدث لملايين الناس كل عام.
I want to use technology that we're all working on and making happen
أريد استخدام التكنولوجيا التي نعمل عليها جميعا لتحقيق ذلك.
to make health care a coordinated team sport.
لجعل الرعاية الصحية عمل منسق بين الفرق.
Now this is the most frightening thing to me.
إليكم أكثر الأشياء التي تخيفني.
Out of all the care I've had in hospitals and clinics around the world,
من بين كل الرعاية الصحية التي حضيت بها في المستشفيات والعيادات في جميع أنحاء العالم،
the first time I've ever had a true team-based care experience
فإن أول مرة حظيت بها على رعاية حقيقية مستندة على فرق عديدة
was at Legacy Good Sam these last six months
كان في مستشفى "ليجاسي جود سام" خلال الأشهر الستة الأخيرة
for me to go get this.
للذهاب والحصول عليه.
And this is a picture of my graduation team from Legacy.
وهذه صورة لفريقي المتخرج من ليجاسي.
There's a couple of the folks here. You'll recognize Dr. Batiuk.
وهناك زوجين من الناس هنا. وبإمكانكم التعرف على الدكتور باتاك.
We just talked to him. Here's Jenny, one of the nurses,
لقد تحدثنا معه للتو . وها هي جيني، واحدة من الممرضات،
Allison, who helped manage the transplant list,
وها هي أليسون، التي ساعدت في إدارة قائمة زرع الأعضاء،
and a dozen other people who aren't pictured,
وعشرات من الناس الآخرين الذين لم يظهروا في الصورة،
a pharmacist, a psychologist, a nutritionist,
صيدلي، أخصائي نفسي، أخصائي تغذية،
even a financial counselor, Lisa,
حتى المستشار المالي، ليزا،
who helped us deal with all the insurance hassles.
التي ساعدتنا على التعامل مع جميع متاعب التأمين.
I wept the day I graduated.
لقد بكيت يوم تخرجت.
I should have been happy, because I was so well
كان ينبغي أن أكون سعيداً، لأنني كنت على ما يرام
that I could go back to my normal doctors,
بأنني سأعود إلى أطبائي الاعتياديين،
but I wept because I was so actually connected to this team.
ولكن أنا بكيت لأنه في الواقع كان متصلاً هذا الفريق.
And here's the most important part.
وها هو الجزء الأكثر أهمية.
The other people in this picture are me and my wife, Ashley.
أشخاص آخرين في هذه الصورة هي لي وزوجتي، أشلي.
Legacy trained us on how to do care for me at home
قامت ليجاسي بتدريبنا على كيفية تقديم الرعاية لي في المنزل
so that they could offload the hospitals and clinics.
ذلك لكي يتمكن من تخفيف العبء على المستشفيات والعيادات.
That's the only way that the model works.
هذا هو السبيل الوحيد الذي يعمل به نموذج العمل.
My team is actually working in China
إن فريقي هذا بدأ يعمل على حالات في الصين
on one of these self-care models
على احد هذه النماذج لتقديم الرعاية الذاتية
for a project we called Age-Friendly Cities.
من ضمن مشروع أسميناه المدن الصديقة للمسنين.
We're trying to help build a social network
نحن نسعى للمساعدة في بناء شبكة اجتماعية
that can help track and train the care of seniors
يمكن لها أن تساعد في تتبع وتدريب الرعاية لكبار السن
caring for themselves
للعناية بأنفسهم
as well as the care provided by their family members
فضلا عن الرعاية المقدمة من قبل أفراد الأسرة
or volunteer community health workers,
أو المتطوعين العاملين في صحة المجتمع،
as well as have an exchange network online,
بالإضافة إلى تشكيل شبكة تبادل مرضى 4على الإنترنت،
where, for example, I can donate three hours of care a day to your mom,
حيث، على سبيل المثال، يمكن أن اتبرع بثلاث ساعات رعاية في اليوم إلى أمك،
if somebody else can help me with transportation to meals,
إذا كان شخص آخر يمكن أن يساعدني بنقل وجبات الطعام،
and we exchange all of that online.
وبإمكاننا تبادل كل ذلك على الإنترنت.
The most important point I want to make to you about this
إن أهم نقطة أريد أن أوضحها لكم بهذا الخصوص
is the sacred and somewhat over-romanticized
هو أن قدسية وينظر لها برومانسية
doctor-patient one-on-one
الطبيب والمريض والعلاقة الشخصية بينهما
is a relic of the past.
هي من مخلفات الماضي.
The future of health care is smart teams,
إن مستقبل الرعاية الصحية هي بالفرق الذكية،
and you'd better be on that team for yourself.
ومن الأجدر أن تكون أنت من ضمن تلك الفرق لمصلحتك.
Now, the last thing that I want to talk to you about
الآن، الشيء الأخير الذي أريد أن أتحدث إليكم عنه
is care customization,
هو تخصيص الرعاية،
because if you've got care anywhere and you've got care networking,
لأنه إذا كنت قد حصلت على الرعاية في أي مكان، وكنت قد حصلت على الرعاية الشبكية،
those are going to go a long way towards improving our health care system,
فإن ذلك الشيئان سيقطعان شوطا طويلاً نحو تحسين نظام الرعاية الصحية لدينا،
but there's still too much guesswork.
ولكن ما زال هناك الكثير من التخمين أمامنا.
Randomized clinical trials were actually invented in 1948
إن التجارب سريرية العشوائية لم تخترع إلا في عام 1948
to help invent the drugs that cured tuberculosis,
للمساعدة في ابتكار العقاقير ضد مرض السل،
and those are important things, don't get me wrong.
وتلك هي من الأمور الهامة، لا تفهموني خطأ.
These population studies that we've done have created
هذه الدراسات السكانية التي قمنا بإجرائها أوجدت لنا
tons of miracle drugs that have saved millions of lives,
أطنان من المخدرات الإعجازية التي أنقذت ملايين الأرواح،
but the problem is that health care
ولكن المشكلة هي أن الرعاية الصحية
is treating us as averages, not unique individuals,
هو علاج للحالات العامة للفرد المتوسط و ليست للحالات الفريدة من نوعها،
because at the end of the day,
لأنه في نهاية اليوم،
the patient is not the same thing as the population
فإن حالة المريض هي ليست نفس حالة بقية الحالات
who are studied. That's what's leading to the guesswork.
التي تمت دراستها. وهذا هو ما يقود إلى عمليات التخمين.
The technologies that are coming,
إن التكنولوجيات القادمة،
high-performance computing, analytics,
في الحوسبة عالية الأداء ، وأدوات التحليل المعلوماتي،
big data that everyone's talking about,
والبيانات الضخمة التي يتحدث عنها الجميع،
will allow us to build predictive models for each of us
سوف تسمح لنا ببناء النماذج التنبؤية لكل واحد منا
as individual patients.
على مستوى كل مريض على حدة.
And the magic here is, experiment on my avatar
والسحر هنا هو، القيام بالتجارب على هيئتي الحاسوبية
in software, not my body in suffering.
في داخل البرمجيات الحاسوبية، وليس على جسدي الذي يعاني.
Now, I've had two examples I want to quickly share with you
الآن، لقد كان لذي مثالين أريد أن أعرضهما عليكم بسرعة
of this kind of care customization on my own journey.
عن هذين النوعين من تخصيص الرعاية في رحلتي.
The first was quite simple. I finally realized some years ago
الأولى كانت في غاية البساطة. وقد أدركت أخيراً منذ بضع سنوات
that all my medical teams were optimizing my treatment for longevity.
أن كل فرقي الطبية كانت تحسن من علاجاتي بغية الاستدامة وتطويل العمر.
It's like a badge of honor to see how long they can get the patient to live.
أنها مثل وسام شرف لمعرفة كم من الوقت يمكن توفيرها للمريض ليحيا فترة أطول.
I was optimizing my life for quality of life,
بينما كنت أحاول أن أحسن حياتي بغية تحسين نوعية الحياة،
and quality of life for me means time in snow.
ونوعية الحياة بالنسبة لي تعني الوقت في الثلج.
So on my chart, I forced them to put, "Patient goal:
وبذلك على نموذج علاجي، أجبرتهم على وضع، "هدف المريض:
low doses of drugs over longer periods of time,
جرعات مخفضة من العقاقير على فترات أطول من الزمن،
side effects friendly to skiing."
الآثار الجانبية: مناسبة للتزلج. "
And I think that's why I achieved longevity.
وأعتقد أن هذا هو السبب الذي حققت به طول العمر.
I think that time-in-snow therapy was as important
وأعتقد أن العلاج "بالوقت في الثلج" لا يقل أهمية عن
as the pharmaceuticals that I had.
الأدوية التي كنت أتناولها.
Now the second example of customization -- and by the way,
الآن المثال الثاني للتخصيص -- وبالمناسبة،
you can't customize care if you don't know your own goals,
لا يمكنك تخصيص الرعاية إذا كنت لا تعرف الأهداف الخاصة بك،
so health care can't know those until you know your own health care goals.
حتى الرعاية الصحية لا يمكنها أن تعرف, حتى تعرف أنت أهداف الرعاية الصحية الخاصة بك.
But the second example I want to give you is,
لكن المثال الثاني الذي أريد أن أعطيكم هو،
I happened to be an early guinea pig,
لقد قُدّر لي أن تكون فأر تجارب منذ وقت مبكر،
and I got very lucky to have my whole genome sequenced.
وقد كنت من المحظوظين الذين حصلوا على خارطة التسلسل الجيني الخاصة بي.
Now it took about two weeks of processing
وللعلم فقد استغرقت حوالي أسبوعين لتجهز
on Intel's highest-end servers to make this happen,
وقد تطلب ذلك استخدام أضخم خوادم معالجات إنتل،
and another six months of human and computing labor
بالإضافة إلى ستة أشهر أخرى من العمل البشري والحاسوبي
to make sense of all of that data.
للوصول إلى معنى مفيد لكل تلك البيانات.
And at the end of all of that, they said, "Yes,
وفي نهاية كل ذلك، قالوا: "نعم،
those diagnoses of that clash of medical titans
كل تلك التشخيصات من صراعات جبابرة الطب أولائك
all of those years ago were wrong,
كل تلك السنوات التي مضت كانت مخطئة،
and we have a better path forward."
واليوم صار لدينا مسار أفضل للسير فيه ".
The future that Intel's working on now is to figure out
إن المستقبل الذي تعمل إنتل من أجله الآن هو لمعرفة
how to make that computing for personalized medicine
كيفية جعل تلك الحوسبة مفيدة تطوير للطب الشخصي وتقصير
go from months and weeks to even hours,
المدي من فترة أشهر وأسابيع لفترة لا تتجاوز حتى الساعات،
and make this kind of tool available,
ولتتيح هذا النوع من الأدوات،
not just in the mainframes of tier-one research hospitals around the world,
ليس فقط في حاسبات المستشفيات ذات المستوى البحثي الأول حول العالم،
but in the mainstream -- every patient, every clinic
بل للسواد العام من المستشفيات-ولكل مريض، وكل عيادة
with access to whole genome sequencing.
بإمكانية الوصول إلى الخارطة الجينية الكاملة.
And I tell you, this kind of care customization
وأنا أقول لكم، هذا النوع من التخصيص في الرعاية
for everything from your goals to your genetics
بكل ما فيها من أهداف خاصة بك وإلى خوارطك الوراثية
will be the most game-changing transformation
كلها ستكون الوسائل لتغيير قواعد اللعبة في عالم الطب الحديث
that we witness in health care during our lifetime.
والتي سنشهد عليها في مجال الرعاية الصحية خلال حياتنا.
So these three pillars of personal health,
لذا فإن هذه الركائز الثلاث للصحة الشخصية،
care anywhere, care networking, care customization,
الرعاية في أي مكان، وشبكات الرعاية، وتخصيص الرعاية ،
are happening in pieces now,
تحدث الآن، في أجزاء
but this vision will completely fail if we don't step up
ولكن هذه الرؤية ستفشل تماما إذا لم نتقدم إلى الأمام
as caregivers and as patients to take on new roles.
لنأخذ أدورنا المناسبة فيها كمقدمين للرعاية وكمرضى .
It's what my friend Verna said:
وهو ما تقوله صديقتي فيرنا :
Wake up and take control of your health.
استيقظ وخذ بزمام السيطرة على صحتك.
Because at the end of the day these technologies
لأنه في نهاية اليوم فإن هذه التكنولوجيات
are simply about people caring for other people
هي ببساطة أناس يقدمون الرعاية لأناس آخرين
and ourselves in some powerful new ways.
ولأنفسنا بطرق جديدة وقوية.
And it's in that spirit that I want to introduce you
ومن هذا المنطلق أريد أن أعرفكم على
to one last friend, very quickly.
صديق أخير ، بشكل سريع.
Tracey Gamley stepped up to give me the impossible kidney
تريسي جامليي التي تقدمت لتعطيني الكلية المستحيلة
that I was never supposed to have.
التي مل يكن من المفترض ابداً أن أحصل عليها.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So Tracey, just tell us a little bit quickly about what the donor experience was like with you.
تريسي، فقط أخبرينا قليلاً وبسرعة حول طبيعة تجربتك كمتبرعة مانحة.
Tracey Gamley: For me, it was really easy.
تريسي جامليي: بالنسبة لي، كانت سهلة حقاً.
I only had one night in the hospital.
لم يكن لدي سوى ليلة واحدة في المستشفى.
The surgery was done laparoscopically,
وقد تمت الجراحة بالمناظير،
so I have just five very small scars on my abdomen,
ولا توجد غير خمس ندبات صغيرة جداً على سطح بطني،
and I had four weeks away from work
ولم أبتعد سوى أربعة أسابيع عن العمل
and went back to doing everything I'd done before
ثم عدت إلى القيام بكل شيء كنت أقوم به من قبل
without any changes.
دون أية تغييرات.
ED: Well, I probably will never get a chance to say this to you
اد: حسنا، أنا ربما لن تحصل على فرصة لقول ذلك لكم
in such a large audience ever again.
في مثل جمهور كبير في أي فرصة يأتي مرة أخرى.
So "thank you" feel likes a really trite word,
لذا فإن كلمة "شكرا لك" تبدو كلمة مبتذلة حقاً،
but thank you from the bottom of my heart for saving my life.
ولكن أشكرك من أعماق قلبي لإنقاذ حياتي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
This TED stage and all of the TED stages
إن مسرح تيد هذا وجميع مسارح تيد
are often about celebrating innovation
غالباً ما تكون حول الاحتفال بالابتكار
and celebrating new technologies,
والاحتفال بالتكنولوجيات الجديدة،
and I've done that here today,
ولقد قمنا بذلك هنا اليوم،
and I've seen amazing things coming from TED speakers,
ولقد رأيت أشياء مدهشة من خطباء تيد،
I mean, my gosh, artificial kidneys, even printable kidneys, that are coming.
أعني، يا إلهي، الكلي الاصطناعية، حتى الكلى باللطباعة، التي ستأتي.
But until such time that these amazing technologies
ولكن إلى أن يحين الوقت لهذه التكنولوجيات المذهلة
are available to all of us, and even when they are,
لنا جميعا، بل وحتى حينما يكونون متوفرين،
it's up to us to care for, and even save, one another.
فإن الأمر مرهون بنا لرعاية أحدنا الأخر، بل وإنقاذ أحدنا الأخر.
I hope you will go out and make personal health happen
أرجو منكم أن تذهبوا وتسهموا في تحقيق الرعاية الصحية الشخصية
for yourselves and for everyone. Thanks so much.
لانفسكم وللجميع. شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)